<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:akn4un="http://un.org/akn4un">
  <!--This is an unofficial copy for informational purposes only and prepared from the official electronic file-->
  <statement name="presidentialStatement">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#DGACM">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-08-07" name="adoption"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="author"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRcountry value="un"></FRBRcountry>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/eng@!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/eng@/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2006-08-07" name="publication"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="issuer"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"></FRBRlanguage>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/eng@/!main.xml"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2006-08-07/2006-37/eng@.xml"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-02-02" name="markup"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="DGACM" as="editor"></FRBRauthor>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="16" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/16" showAs="sdg_16" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="civil_society" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/8428" showAs="civil_society" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="civil_society" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1001012" showAs="civil_society" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="justice" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003500" showAs="justice" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="peaceful_coexistence" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1004777" showAs="peaceful_coexistence" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="social_justice" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005970" showAs="social_justice" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/5585" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1006319" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="right_to_justice" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/516" showAs="right_to_justice" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="public_institution" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/878" showAs="public_institution" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="public_institution" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005254" showAs="public_institution" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="9" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/9" showAs="sdg_9" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="industrialization" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003177" showAs="industrialization" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="industrial_infrastructure" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/1434" showAs="industrial_infrastructure" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="innovation" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/1439" showAs="innovation" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="innovation" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003223" showAs="innovation" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <workflow source="#un">
        <step />
      </workflow>
      <analysis source="#un">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting>
            <quorum value=""></quorum>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#DGACM">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/DGACM" showAs="DGACM"></TLCOrganization>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfIssuance" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfIssuance" showAs="Date of issuance"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfAdoption" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfAdoption" showAs="Date of adoption"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="symbol" href="/akn/ontology/reference/un/symbol" showAs="Symbol"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCRole eId="publisher" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/publisher" showAs="Publisher"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="issuingBody" href="/akn/role/concept/un/issuingBody" showAs="Issuing body"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/author" showAs="Author"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/editor" showAs="Editor"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="distribution" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/generalDistribution" showAs="General distribution"></TLCRole>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sc" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/securityCouncil" showAs="Security Council"></TLCOrganization>
      </references>
      <presentation source="#un">
        <akn4un:footerFirstPage>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
            <akn4un:internalCode>
              <docketNumber refersTo="#publicationJobNumber">06-45699 (E)</docketNumber>
              <img alt="bar code" class="barCode" src=""></img>
            </akn4un:internalCode>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
            <img alt="Please recycle" class="image" src="./recylcleLogo.jpg"></img>
            <img alt="embedded QR code" class="qrCode" src=""></img>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
        </akn4un:footerFirstPage>
      </presentation>
    </meta>
    <coverPage eId="coverPage_1">
      <p>
        <span refersTo="#publisher" class="upperLeft">
          <docAuthority refersTo="#publisher">United Nations</docAuthority>
        </span>
      </p>
      <p class="upperRight">
        <docNumber refersTo="#symbol">S/PRST/2006/37</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="upperLeft">
        <img src="logo-un.jpg"></img>
        <docAuthority refersTo="#issuingBody" class="rightBig">Security Council</docAuthority>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docStatus refersTo="#generalDistribution" class="rightSmall">Distr.: General</docStatus>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docDate date="2006-08-07" class="rightSmall" refersTo="#dateOfIssuance">7 August 2006</docDate>
      </p>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p />
    </preface>
    <mainBody>
      <p>
      <docTitle refersTo="#title1">
        <span class="bold">		Statement by the President of the Security Council</span>
      </docTitle>
      </p>
      <alinea>
        <content eId="alinea_1__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	At the 5505th meeting of the Security Council, held on 7 August 2006, in connection with the Council’s consideration of the item entitled “The situation in Côte d’Ivoire”, the President of the Security Council made the following statement on behalf of the Council:</p>
        </content>
      </alinea>
      <paragraph eId="para_3" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_3__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council affirms its commitment to the implementation of the peace process and of the roadmap established by the International Working Group (IWG). It welcomes the initiatives of the Prime Minister, Mr. Charles Konan Banny, and the ongoing dialogue among President Laurent Gbagbo, the Prime Minister and all other Ivorian parties.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_4" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_4__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reiterates its full support for the Prime Minister. It welcomes his determination to implement the decisions taken by all Ivorian parties at the high level meeting held in Yamoussoukro on 5 July 2006. It strongly encourages him to continue his efforts and demands that all Ivorian parties cooperate with him fully and in good faith.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_5" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_5__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council welcomes the launch of the mobile courts throughout Côte d’Ivoire and the Prime Minister’s announcement of the completion of the pre‑cantonment of the Defense and Security Forces of Côte d’Ivoire and of the Armed Forces of the Forces Nouvelles. The Security Council further welcomes the establishment of the disarmament, demobilization and reintegration (DDR) Monitoring Group, the measures taken to implement the quadripartite control of pre‑cantonment operations and the beginning of operations to dismantle and disarm the militias. It takes note of the signing of a Presidential decree allowing the Independent Electoral Commission (IEC) to propose any technical adjustments to the electoral code for the transitional elections.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_6" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_6__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council expresses its concern that the IEC’s structures have not been deployed throughout the country as well as the local offices of the National Commission of Supervision of the Identification. It urges the Ivorian parties to settle these issues without delay.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_7" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_7__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council strongly condemns the obstructions to the normal functioning of the mobile courts which followed the calls for such action made by political leaders, in particular the Chairman of the FPI and the President of the former National Assembly. It notes that the procedures of the mobile courts were decided in consultation with President Laurent Gbagbo. It urges all parties to ensure that the mobile courts function without further hindrance.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_8" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_8__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council expresses its utmost concern and condemns the acts of violence committed by organized groups, in particular the Young Patriots, which led to the deaths of civilians, and further condemns the attack of 24 July against the High Representative for the Elections, despite the presence of the Republican Guard at the scene.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_9" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_9__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council condemns also the incidents of 15 July at the premises of the Radio Télévision Ivoirienne (RTI). It calls on the Ivorian authorities to strengthen security measures at RTI. It underlines the importance of guaranteeing the independence and neutrality of the media in Côte d’Ivoire.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_10" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_10__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reaffirms its support for the implementation of measures against those responsible as provided for in paragraphs 9 and 11 of resolution 1572 (2004) and underlines that the reports of the events described above will be examined by the Sanctions Committee established by paragraph 14 of resolution 1572 (2004).</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_11" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_11__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council demands that the Defense and Security Forces of Côte d’Ivoire, including the Republican Guard, act within the law of the land at all times to ensure full security of the population, including foreigners, and support the implementation of the roadmap led by the Prime Minister. It reaffirms in this regard paragraphs 8 and 9 of resolution 1633 (2005). It recalls that the Defense and Security Forces and the Forces Nouvelles must ensure the security of the mobile courts hearings in the areas under their control.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_12" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_12__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council demands also that all Ivorian parties cooperate fully in the operations of the Impartial Forces, in particular by guaranteeing the safety, security and freedom of movement of their personnel, as well as associated personnel, throughout the territory of Côte d’Ivoire, and affirms that any obstacle to their freedom of movement or to the full implementation of their mandates will not be tolerated. It recalls paragraph 4 of resolution 1643 (2005) in this regard.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_13" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_13__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reaffirms the importance of the concomitant implementation of the identification and DDR operations and of the acceleration by all Ivorian parties of the implementation of the roadmap in order to create the conditions indispensable for the holding of free, open, fair and transparent elections within the agreed timetable.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_14" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_14__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council therefore considers that it is necessary to deploy throughout the territory of Côte d’Ivoire as many mobile courts as possible towards the objective of 150 mobile courts called for in the Prime Minister’s plan and to complete the second phase of the DDR programme, the cantonment of combatants, before the next meeting of the IWG. It encourages the Prime Minister to take all the necessary actions to this end, with the agreement of all Ivorian parties, as well as for the organization of the elections. It calls on the IWG to monitor such progress and to report to it on its assessment of the progress made.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_15" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_15__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council expresses its full support for the IWG and endorses its ninth communiqué dated 20 July 2006. It reiterates its full support for the Special Representative of the Secretary-General and the High Representative for the Elections.”</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </mainBody>
  </statement>
</akomaNtoso>