<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:akn4un="http://un.org/akn4un">
  <!--This is an unofficial copy for informational purposes only and prepared from the official electronic file-->
  <statement name="presidentialStatement">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#DGACM">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2001-01-31" name="adoption"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="author"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRcountry value="un"></FRBRcountry>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/eng@!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/eng@/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2001-01-31" name="publication"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="issuer"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"></FRBRlanguage>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/eng@/!main.xml"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2001-01-31/2001-3/eng@.xml"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-02-02" name="markup"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="DGACM" as="editor"></FRBRauthor>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <workflow source="#un">
        <step />
      </workflow>
      <analysis source="#un">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting>
            <quorum value=""></quorum>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#DGACM">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/DGACM" showAs="DGACM"></TLCOrganization>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfIssuance" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfIssuance" showAs="Date of issuance"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfAdoption" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfAdoption" showAs="Date of adoption"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="symbol" href="/akn/ontology/reference/un/symbol" showAs="Symbol"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCRole eId="publisher" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/publisher" showAs="Publisher"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="issuingBody" href="/akn/role/concept/un/issuingBody" showAs="Issuing body"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/author" showAs="Author"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/editor" showAs="Editor"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="distribution" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/generalDistribution" showAs="General distribution"></TLCRole>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sc" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/securityCouncil" showAs="Security Council"></TLCOrganization>
      </references>
      <presentation source="#un">
        <akn4un:footerFirstPage>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
            <akn4un:internalCode>
              <docketNumber refersTo="#publicationJobNumber">01-23427 (E)</docketNumber>
              <img alt="bar code" class="barCode" src=""></img>
            </akn4un:internalCode>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
            <img alt="Please recycle" class="image" src="./recylcleLogo.jpg"></img>
            <img alt="embedded QR code" class="qrCode" src=""></img>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
        </akn4un:footerFirstPage>
      </presentation>
    </meta>
    <coverPage eId="coverPage_1">
      <p>
        <span refersTo="#publisher" class="upperLeft">
          <docAuthority refersTo="#publisher">United Nations</docAuthority>
        </span>
      </p>
      <p class="upperRight">
        <docNumber refersTo="#symbol">S/PRST/2001/3</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="upperLeft">
        <img src="logo-un.jpg"></img>
        <docAuthority refersTo="#issuingBody" class="rightBig">Security Council</docAuthority>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docStatus refersTo="#generalDistribution" class="rightSmall">Distr.: General</docStatus>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docDate date="2001-01-31" class="rightSmall" refersTo="#dateOfIssuance">31 January 2001</docDate>
      </p>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p />
    </preface>
    <mainBody>
      <paragraph eId="para_1" class="H1">
        <span class="bold">		Statement by the President of the Security Council</span>
      </docTitle>
      </p>
      <alinea>
        <content eId="alinea_1__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	At the 4270th meeting of the Security Council, held on 31 January 2001, in connection with the Council’s consideration of the item entitled “Strengthening cooperation with troop-contributing countries”, the President of the Security Council made the following statement on behalf of the Council:</p>
        </content>
      </alinea>
      <paragraph eId="para_3" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_3__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council has given further consideration to the question of strengthening cooperation between the Council, the troop-contributing countries and the Secretariat. In this connection, the Council stresses the importance of full implementation of provisions of resolution 1327 (2000) of 13 November 2000 and in the statements of its President of 28 March 1996 (S/PRST/1996/13) and 3 May 1994 (S/PRST/1994/22). The Council takes note of the views expressed at its debate on the subject ‘Strengthening Cooperation with Troop-Contributing Countries’ at its 4257th meeting on 16 January 2001. The Council recognizes the scope for further improvement in its relations with troop-contributing countries and the need to work together with a common purpose towards shared goals.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_4" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_4__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council recognizes that in view of the increasing complexity of peacekeeping operations, there is a need for a transparent three-way relationship between the Security Council, the Secretariat and the troop-contributing countries that will foster a new spirit of partnership, cooperation and confidence.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_5" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_5__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“Recognizing that the experience and expertise of troop-contributing countries in theatres of operation can greatly assist the planning process, the Security Council reiterates its agreement to hold consultations with troop-contributing countries in a timely manner at different stages of a United Nations peacekeeping operation, in particular when the Secretary-General has identified potential troop-contributing countries for a new or ongoing peacekeeping operation, during the implementation phase of an operation, when considering a change to, or renewal of, or completion of a peacekeeping mandate, or when a rapid deterioration in the situation on the ground threatens the safety and security of United Nations peacekeepers.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_6" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_6__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council will seek to ensure that all private meetings as provided for in resolution 1327 (2000) between members of the Council, the troop-contributing countries and the Secretariat are substantive, representative, meaningful and provide for a full exchange of views. The Council stresses the importance of full participation by all those involved and encourages troop-contributing countries to take the initiative to call for meaningful exchanges of information. The President of the Council will provide, where appropriate, a detailed report of consultations with the troop-contributing countries to the Council.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_7" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_7__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council stresses the usefulness of full and comprehensive briefings by the Secretariat at private meetings with the troop-contributing countries, including, where appropriate, military factors.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_8" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_8__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council encourages the Secretary-General to continue his efforts to improve coordination and cooperation on peacekeeping issues within the United Nations system and the Secretariat.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_9" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_9__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council encourages the Secretary-General to raise public awareness globally of the positive contribution of peacekeeping operations and the role played by peacekeepers from various troop-contributing countries.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_10" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_10__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council acknowledges that the Secretariat must be able to rely on sufficient human and financial resources to respond to the demands placed on it. It underlines the importance of follow-up to the report of the Panel on Peace Operations (S/2000/809) with a view to strengthening the Department of Peacekeeping Operations and other relevant departments of the Secretariat involved in peacekeeping.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_11" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_11__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council reiterates that the problem of the commitment gap with regard to personnel and equipment for peacekeeping operations requires the assumption by all Member States of the shared responsibility to support United Nations peacekeeping.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_12" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_12__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council acknowledges that the delay in reimbursement causes severe budgetary constraints to troop-contributing countries. It urges all Member States to pay their assessed contributions in full and on time, so that peacekeeping operations can stand on a solid financial basis.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_13" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_13__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council decides to establish a Working Group of the Whole on United Nations peacekeeping operations. The Working Group will not replace the private meetings with the troop-contributing countries. The Working Group will address both generic peacekeeping issues relevant to the responsibilities of the Council, and technical aspects of individual peacekeeping operations, without prejudice to the competence of the Special Committee on Peacekeeping Operations. Where appropriate, the Working Group will seek the views of the troop-contributing countries, including through meetings between the Working Group and the troop-contributing countries, with a view to their views being taken into account by the Council.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_14" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_14__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“As a first step, the Working Group is tasked to undertake an in-depth consideration of, inter alia, all the proposals made in the course of the Council’s public meeting on 16 January 2001, including ways to improve the three-way relationship between the Council, the troop-contributing countries and the Secretariat and to report to the Council by 30 April 2001. An indicative list of all the ideas and proposals arising from the meeting on 16 January 2001 will be forwarded to the Working Group for its consideration.”</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </mainBody>
  </statement>
</akomaNtoso>