<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:akn4un="http://un.org/akn4un">
  <!--This is an unofficial copy for informational purposes only and prepared from the official electronic file-->
  <statement name="presidentialStatement">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#DGACM">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-09-04" name="adoption"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="author"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRcountry value="un"></FRBRcountry>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/eng@!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/eng@/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-09-04" name="publication"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="issuer"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"></FRBRlanguage>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/eng@/!main.xml"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-09-04/2008-33/eng@.xml"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-02-02" name="markup"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="DGACM" as="editor"></FRBRauthor>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <workflow source="#un">
        <step />
      </workflow>
      <analysis source="#un">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting>
            <quorum value=""></quorum>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#DGACM">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/DGACM" showAs="DGACM"></TLCOrganization>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfIssuance" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfIssuance" showAs="Date of issuance"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfAdoption" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfAdoption" showAs="Date of adoption"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="symbol" href="/akn/ontology/reference/un/symbol" showAs="Symbol"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCRole eId="publisher" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/publisher" showAs="Publisher"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="issuingBody" href="/akn/role/concept/un/issuingBody" showAs="Issuing body"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/author" showAs="Author"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/editor" showAs="Editor"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="distribution" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/generalDistribution" showAs="General distribution"></TLCRole>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sc" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/securityCouncil" showAs="Security Council"></TLCOrganization>
      </references>
      <presentation source="#un">
        <akn4un:footerFirstPage>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
            <akn4un:internalCode>
              <docketNumber refersTo="#publicationJobNumber">08-49747 (E)</docketNumber>
              <img alt="bar code" class="barCode" src=""></img>
            </akn4un:internalCode>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
            <img alt="Please recycle" class="image" src="./recylcleLogo.jpg"></img>
            <img alt="embedded QR code" class="qrCode" src=""></img>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
        </akn4un:footerFirstPage>
      </presentation>
    </meta>
    <coverPage eId="coverPage_1">
      <p>
        <span refersTo="#publisher" class="upperLeft">
          <docAuthority refersTo="#publisher">United Nations</docAuthority>
        </span>
      </p>
      <p class="upperRight">
        <docNumber refersTo="#symbol">S/PRST/2008/33</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="upperLeft">
        <img src="logo-un.jpg"></img>
        <docAuthority refersTo="#issuingBody" class="rightBig">Security Council</docAuthority>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docStatus refersTo="#generalDistribution" class="rightSmall">Distr.: General</docStatus>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docDate date="2008-09-04" class="rightSmall" refersTo="#dateOfIssuance">4 September 2008</docDate>
      </p>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p />
    </preface>
    <mainBody>
      <p>
      <docTitle refersTo="#title1">
        <span class="bold">		Statement by the President of the Security Council</span>
      </docTitle>
      </p>
      <alinea>
        <content eId="alinea_1__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	At the 5970th meeting of the Security Council, held on 4 September 2008, in connection with the Council’s consideration of the item entitled “The situation in Somalia”, the President of the Security Council made the following statement on behalf of the Council:</p>
        </content>
      </alinea>
      <paragraph eId="para_3" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_3__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council welcomes the signing of a peace and reconciliation Agreement (“the Djibouti Agreement”) between the Transitional Federal Government (TFG) and the Alliance for the Re-Liberation of Somalia (ARS) in Djibouti on 19 August 2008, the preliminary work undertaken by the High Level Committee and the Joint Security Committee set up under that Agreement, as well as recent political developments. The Security Council expresses its determination that the Agreement should provide the basis for lasting peace, security and stability for the people of Somalia, including the ultimate withdrawal of foreign forces. The Security Council commends the efforts deployed by the TFG and the ARS to this end and their commitment to peace. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_4" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_4__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reaffirms its respect for the sovereignty, territorial integrity, political independence and unity of Somalia.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_5" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_5__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council extends its gratitude to the Special Representative of the Secretary-General for Somalia, Mr Ahmedou Ould-Abdallah, and to the UN Political Office for Somalia for mediating dialogue between the parties and garnering support for the political process. The Security Council further expresses its gratitude to the Government of Djibouti for hosting talks between the parties.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_6" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_6__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council calls on the parties to meet all elements of their Agreement in full. In particular, the Council underlines the crucial importance of the parties taking all necessary measures to ensure, without delay, unhindered humanitarian access and assistance to the Somali people, and of the parties and their allies terminating all acts of armed confrontation. The Security Council states its support for the implementation of the Agreement and its intention to review that implementation continuously. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_7" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_7__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reiterates its strong support for the African Union Mission to Somalia (AMISOM) and urges again the international community to provide financial resources, personnel, equipment and services for the full deployment of AMISOM.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_8" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_8__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council takes note of the parties’ request in the Djibouti Agreement that the United Nations, within a period of 120 days, authorise and deploy an international stabilisation force. The Council further notes, in this regard, communiqués by the Peace and Security Council of the African Union of 29 June 2008, 8 August 2008 and 20 August 2008.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_9" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_9__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council, acknowledging recent positive political developments in the wake of the Djibouti Agreement as confirmed by Mr Ould-Abdallah, reaffirms its willingness, as set out in its resolution 1814 (2008), to consider, at an appropriate time, a United Nations peacekeeping operation to take over from AMISOM, subject to progress in the political process and improvement in the security situation on the ground. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_10" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_10__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council recalls the Secretary-General’s contingency planning for a United Nations integrated peacekeeping mission in Somalia, which recommends that plans are put in place for the deployment of an international stabilisation force, in the framework of the approach presented by the Secretary-General in his report of 14 March 2008 (S/2008/178).</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_11" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_11__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“In this regard, the Security Council requests that the Secretary-General elaborate on his contingency plans and provide, in consultation with the parties and other relevant stakeholders, a detailed and consolidated description of a feasible multinational force, its mandate and derived tasks, to include inter alia the size and geographical scope of that force, progressively deployed, and further provide a detailed concept of operations for a feasible United Nations peacekeeping operation. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_12" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_12__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council further requests the Secretary-General urgently to identify and approach States that might contribute the financial resources, personnel, equipment and services required, stands ready to support the Secretary-General in this regard, and calls upon States to respond favourably.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_13" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_13__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council requests the Secretary-General to report on the implementation of the Djibouti Agreement by the parties, including an update on the conditions on the ground, as well as on his planning, including discussions with potential contributing States, within 60 days.”</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </mainBody>
  </statement>
</akomaNtoso>