<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:akn4un="http://un.org/akn4un">
  <!--This is an unofficial copy for informational purposes only and prepared from the official electronic file-->
  <statement name="presidentialStatement">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#DGACM">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-11-07" name="adoption"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="author"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRcountry value="un"></FRBRcountry>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/eng@!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/eng@/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2008-11-07" name="publication"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="issuer"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"></FRBRlanguage>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/eng@/!main.xml"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2008-11-07/2008-42/eng@.xml"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-02-02" name="markup"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="DGACM" as="editor"></FRBRauthor>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <workflow source="#un">
        <step />
      </workflow>
      <analysis source="#un">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting>
            <quorum value=""></quorum>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#DGACM">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/DGACM" showAs="DGACM"></TLCOrganization>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfIssuance" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfIssuance" showAs="Date of issuance"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfAdoption" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfAdoption" showAs="Date of adoption"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="symbol" href="/akn/ontology/reference/un/symbol" showAs="Symbol"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCRole eId="publisher" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/publisher" showAs="Publisher"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="issuingBody" href="/akn/role/concept/un/issuingBody" showAs="Issuing body"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/author" showAs="Author"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/editor" showAs="Editor"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="distribution" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/generalDistribution" showAs="General distribution"></TLCRole>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sc" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/securityCouncil" showAs="Security Council"></TLCOrganization>
      </references>
      <presentation source="#un">
        <akn4un:footerFirstPage>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
            <akn4un:internalCode>
              <docketNumber refersTo="#publicationJobNumber">08-59389 (E)</docketNumber>
              <img alt="bar code" class="barCode" src=""></img>
            </akn4un:internalCode>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
            <img alt="Please recycle" class="image" src="./recylcleLogo.jpg"></img>
            <img alt="embedded QR code" class="qrCode" src=""></img>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
        </akn4un:footerFirstPage>
      </presentation>
    </meta>
    <coverPage eId="coverPage_1">
      <p>
        <span refersTo="#publisher" class="upperLeft">
          <docAuthority refersTo="#publisher">United Nations</docAuthority>
        </span>
      </p>
      <p class="upperRight">
        <docNumber refersTo="#symbol">S/PRST/2008/42</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="upperLeft">
        <img src="logo-un.jpg"></img>
        <docAuthority refersTo="#issuingBody" class="rightBig">Security Council</docAuthority>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docStatus refersTo="#generalDistribution" class="rightSmall">Distr.: General</docStatus>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docDate date="2008-11-07" class="rightSmall" refersTo="#dateOfIssuance">7 November 2008</docDate>
      </p>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p />
    </preface>
    <mainBody>
      <p>
      <docTitle refersTo="#title1">
        <span class="bold">		Statement by the President of the Security Council</span>
      </docTitle>
      </p>
      <alinea>
        <content eId="alinea_1__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	At the 6014th meeting of the Security Council, held on 7 November 2008, in connection with the Council’s consideration of the item entitled “The situation in Côte d’Ivoire”, the President of the Security Council made the following statement on behalf of the Council:</p>
        </content>
      </alinea>
      <paragraph eId="para_3" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_3__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council takes note that, as mentioned in the report of the Secretary-General dated 14 October, the peace process has crossed a critical milestone with the launching of the identification and registration of voters operations on 15 September 2008. It also however notes that the delays occurred since the launch of the identification and voter registration processes on 15 September 2008 have proven greater than expected. It takes note that the Special Representative of the Secretary-General indicated on the 27 October 2008 that, if the elections scheduled for the 30 November 2008 were delayed, they were likely to be delayed by several months, due mainly to some logistical difficulties. The Security Council expresses its deep concern about a possible third consecutive delay since the signature of the Ouagadougou Political Agreement, which could put at risk the entire Ivorian peace process.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_4" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_4__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council commends the Facilitator for convening a meeting of the permanent consultative framework on the 10 November 2008, in order for the Ivorian political actors to address all the main difficulties of the electoral process, and in particular with a view to finding an agreement on the new electoral time frame. It urges all the Ivorian political actors to cooperate fully with the Facilitator, with the support of the Special Representative of the Secretary-General, and to demonstrate their political determination to fulfil the commitments taken in the Ouagadougou agreement and in the framework of its follow-up mechanisms.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_5" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_5__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council further urges to this end the President of the Independent Electoral Commission, which is in charge of the organization of the elections, to share publicly this new timeline, including in particular the full roll out of the identification process and some other stages such as the publication of the provisional and final versions of the electoral list, the fabrication and distribution of the identity and voter’s cards and the date of the presidential election. It emphasizes that all political actors must pay a particular attention to the accumulating logistical delay.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_6" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_6__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council urges the Ivorian parties to take immediately and as a priority the concrete steps necessary to complete the identification and registration of voters operations in a credible and transparent manner before the end of January 2009. It expresses its determination to bring its full support to a credible electoral process in Côte d’Ivoire, on the understanding that the presidential elections will be organized before the end of spring 2009. The Security Council recalls that all political parties agreed to abide by the Code of Good Conduct for elections they signed under the auspices of the Secretary‑General on the 23 April 2008.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_7" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_7__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council recalls that, pursuant to resolutions 1572 (2004) and 1842 (2008), any threat to the electoral process in Côte d’Ivoire shall constitute a threat to the peace and national reconciliation process and it reaffirms its determination to impose targeted measures against any person designated by its Sanctions Committee concerning Côte d’Ivoire to be responsible for these threats. The Security Council expresses its willingness to review the sanctions regime at the latest three months after the presidential elections.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_8" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_8__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">		“The Security Council requests the Secretary-General to keep it informed of the evolution of the situation. It reaffirms its full support to the efforts of his Special Representative and his certification mandate, including the explicit certification of the electoral list. It expresses its intention to take the progress of the electoral process fully into consideration when it will review the mandate of UNOCI and the French forces which support it, before 31 January 2009.”</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </mainBody>
  </statement>
</akomaNtoso>