<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0 http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/akn-core/v1.0/os/part2-specs/schemas/akomantoso30.xsd" xmlns="http://docs.oasis-open.org/legaldocml/ns/akn/3.0" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:akn4un="http://un.org/akn4un">
  <!--This is an unofficial copy for informational purposes only and prepared from the official electronic file-->
  <statement name="presidentialStatement">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#DGACM">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-03-12" name="adoption"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="author"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRcountry value="un"></FRBRcountry>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/eng@!main/"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/eng@/"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2003-03-12" name="publication"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="sc" as="issuer"></FRBRauthor>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"></FRBRlanguage>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/eng@/!main.xml"></FRBRthis>
          <FRBRuri value="/akn/un/statement/deliberation/unsc/2003-03-12/2003-2/eng@.xml"></FRBRuri>
          <FRBRdate date="2024-02-02" name="markup"></FRBRdate>
          <FRBRauthor href="DGACM" as="editor"></FRBRauthor>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="16" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/16" showAs="sdg_16" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="public_institution" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/878" showAs="public_institution" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="public_institution" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005254" showAs="public_institution" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="civil_society" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/8428" showAs="civil_society" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="civil_society" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1001012" showAs="civil_society" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="justice" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003500" showAs="justice" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="peaceful_coexistence" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1004777" showAs="peaceful_coexistence" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="social_justice" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005970" showAs="social_justice" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/5585" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1006319" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="right_to_justice" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/516" showAs="right_to_justice" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="5" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/5" showAs="sdg_5" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="women" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1007029" showAs="women" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="gender_equality" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/3913" showAs="gender_equality" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="gender_equality" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1002612" showAs="gender_equality" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="girls" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1002684" showAs="girls" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="women's_rights" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/585" showAs="women's_rights" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="women's_rights" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1007035" showAs="women's_rights" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="participation_of_women" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/2265" showAs="participation_of_women" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="position_of_women" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/81" showAs="position_of_women" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="1" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/1" showAs="sdg_1" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="poverty" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/2281" showAs="poverty" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="poverty" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005064" showAs="poverty" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="poverty_mitigation" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1005065" showAs="poverty_mitigation" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="9" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/9" showAs="sdg_9" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="industrialization" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003177" showAs="industrialization" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="industrial_infrastructure" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/1434" showAs="industrial_infrastructure" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="innovation" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/1439" showAs="innovation" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="innovation" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1003223" showAs="innovation" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <classification source="https://metadata.un.org/sdg">
        <keyword value="17" href="http://metadata.un.org/sdg/17" showAs="sdg_17" dictionary="SDGO"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/5585" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="sustainable_development" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1006319" showAs="sustainable_development" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
        <keyword value="partnership" href="http://eurovoc.europa.eu/4199" showAs="partnership" dictionary="EuroVoc"></keyword>
        <keyword value="partnership" href="http://metadata.un.org/thesaurus/1004748" showAs="partnership" dictionary="UNBIS"></keyword>
      </classification>
      <workflow source="#un">
        <step />
      </workflow>
      <analysis source="#un">
        <parliamentary>
          <voting>
            <quorum value=""></quorum>
          </voting>
        </parliamentary>
      </analysis>
      <references source="#DGACM">
        <TLCOrganization eId="source" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/DGACM" showAs="DGACM"></TLCOrganization>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfIssuance" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfIssuance" showAs="Date of issuance"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="dateOfAdoption" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/dateOfAdoption" showAs="Date of adoption"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCConcept eId="symbol" href="/akn/ontology/reference/un/symbol" showAs="Symbol"></TLCConcept>
        <TLCRole eId="publisher" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/publisher" showAs="Publisher"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="issuingBody" href="/akn/role/concept/un/issuingBody" showAs="Issuing body"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="author" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/author" showAs="Author"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="editor" href="/akn/ontology/role/un/editor" showAs="Editor"></TLCRole>
        <TLCRole eId="distribution" href="/akn/ontology/concept/un/generalDistribution" showAs="General distribution"></TLCRole>
        <TLCOrganization eId="sc" href="/akn/ontology/organization/un/securityCouncil" showAs="Security Council"></TLCOrganization>
      </references>
      <presentation source="#un">
        <akn4un:footerFirstPage>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
            <akn4un:internalCode>
              <docketNumber refersTo="#publicationJobNumber">03-27746 (E)</docketNumber>
              <img alt="bar code" class="barCode" src=""></img>
            </akn4un:internalCode>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageLeft>
          <akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
            <img alt="Please recycle" class="image" src="./recylcleLogo.jpg"></img>
            <img alt="embedded QR code" class="qrCode" src=""></img>
          </akn4un:footerFirstPageRight>
        </akn4un:footerFirstPage>
      </presentation>
    </meta>
    <coverPage eId="coverPage_1">
      <p>
        <span refersTo="#publisher" class="upperLeft">
          <docAuthority refersTo="#publisher">United Nations</docAuthority>
        </span>
      </p>
      <p class="upperRight">
        <docNumber refersTo="#symbol">S/PRST/2003/2</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="upperLeft">
        <img src="logo-un.jpg"></img>
        <docAuthority refersTo="#issuingBody" class="rightBig">Security Council</docAuthority>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docStatus refersTo="#generalDistribution" class="rightSmall">Distr.: General</docStatus>
      </p>
      <p>
        <docDate date="2003-03-12" class="rightSmall" refersTo="#dateOfIssuance">12 March 2003</docDate>
      </p>
    </coverPage>
    <preface>
      <p />
    </preface>
    <mainBody>
      <paragraph eId="para_1" class="H1">
        <span class="bold">		Statement by the President of the Security Council</span>
      </docTitle>
      </p>
      <alinea>
        <content eId="alinea_1__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	At the 4718th meeting of the Security Council, held on 12 March 2003, in connection with the Council’s consideration of the item entitled “The situation in Somalia”, the President of the Security Council made the following statement on behalf of the Council:</p>
        </content>
      </alinea>
      <paragraph eId="para_3" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_3__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council, recalling its previous decisions concerning the situation in Somalia, in particular the statements of its President of 13 December 2002 (S/PRST/2002/35) and of 28 March 2002 (S/PRST/2002/8), and welcoming the report of the Secretary-General of 26 February 2003 (S/2003/231), reaffirms its commitment to a comprehensive and lasting settlement of the situation in Somalia, and its respect for the sovereignty, territorial integrity, political independence and unity of the country, consistent with the purposes and principles of the Charter of the United Nations. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_4" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_4__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reiterates its firm support for the Somali National Reconciliation Process and the ongoing Somali National Reconciliation Conference in Kenya, launched under the auspices of the Intergovernmental Authority on Development (IGAD) and led by the Government of Kenya. The Council strongly encourages all parties throughout Somalia to participate in the process, which offers a unique opportunity for all Somalis to end the suffering of their people and to restore peace and stability to their country. The Council demands the Somalia parties to abide by and implement expeditiously the decisions adopted throughout the process, including the Declaration on Cessation of Hostilities and the Structures and Principles of the Somali National Reconciliation Process, on 27 October 2002, hereafter referred to as the ‘Eldoret Declaration’ (S/2002/1359), as well as the December 2002 agreement reached by five Mogadishu faction leaders and the Transitional National Government regarding the restoration of peace and security in Mogadishu and a subsequent agreement among the five faction leaders which included a commitment to make efforts to reopen the International Airport and Seaport in Mogadishu, as mentioned in paragraph 26 of the report of the Secretary-General of 26 February 2003 (S/2003/231).</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_5" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_5__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council commends the Government of Kenya for its crucial role in facilitating the Somali National Reconciliation Process, and calls on the IGAD Technical Committee comprised of the three Frontline States (Djibouti, Ethiopia and Kenya) to continue their active role in promoting the Process. The Council welcomes the appointment of Ambassador Bethuel Kiplagat as the Special Envoy of Kenya to the Process. The Council also welcomes the appointment of Mr. Muhammad Ali Foum as the Special Envoy of the African Union for Somalia, the generous financial contribution of the European Union, Norway and the US, and the sustained engagement of their envoys, as well as those of the IGAD Partners Forum and the League of Arab States. The Council strongly encourages their continued active and positive role in support of the reconciliation process.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_6" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_6__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council notes that the six reconciliation committees of the Somali National Reconciliation Process have continued their work despite difficulties faced by the Somali participants regarding representation. The Council urges all parties involved to fully participate in the six reconciliation committees and to resolve the representation issue, and welcomes the establishment of an arbitration committee in this regard. The Council supports the Secretary-General’s commitment to assist in the work of the six reconciliation committees with technical support and relevant expertise. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_7" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_7__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council expresses its strong regret that even after the signing of the ‘Eldoret Declaration’, fighting continued to break out in Somalia in particular in Mogadishu and Baidoa. The Council condemns all those involved in the fighting and calls for an immediate end to all acts of violence in Somalia. The Council shares the Secretary-General’s conclusion that it is those that have weapons of war who continue to hold the people of Somalia hostage to the cycle of violence. The Council also shares the Secretary-General’s view that these people will be held accountable by the Somali people and the international community for their actions if they persist on the path of confrontation and conflict. In this regard, the Security Council welcomes the establishment of a mechanism by the IGAD Frontline States to monitor compliance with the ‘Eldoret Declaration’ and their intention to consider appropriate measures against all individuals and groups violating the ‘Eldoret Declaration’ and December 2002 agreements.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_8" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_8__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council notes with serious concern the continued flow of weapons and ammunition supplies to Somalia, as well as allegations of the role of some of the neighbouring States in breach of the arms embargo established by resolution 733 (1992) of 23 January 1992, and calls on all States and other actors to comply scrupulously with the arms embargo. The Council welcomes the work of the Panel of Experts, established pursuant to resolution 1425 (2002) of 22 July 2002, and expresses its intention to give full consideration to and take appropriate action regarding the Panel’s report as a step towards reinforcing the arms embargo and disarmament.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_9" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_9__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council, insisting that persons and entities must not be allowed to take advantage of the situation in Somalia to finance, plan, facilitate, support or commit terrorist acts from the country, emphasizes that efforts to combat terrorism in Somalia are inseparable from the establishment of peace and governance in the country. In this spirit, the Council urges the international community to provide assistance to Somalia for the further and comprehensive implementation of resolution 1373 (2001).</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_10" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_10__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council expresses serious concern regarding the humanitarian situation in Somalia, in particular the internally displaced persons, especially in the area of Mogadishu. The Council urges the Somalia leaders to live up to their commitments under the ‘Eldoret Declaration’, to facilitate the delivery of much-needed humanitarian assistance, to assure the safety of all international and national aid workers, to provide immediate safe access for all humanitarian personnel, and to support the return and reintegration of refugees. The Council calls on Member States to respond urgently and generously to the United Nations Consolidated Inter-Agency Appeal for 2003. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_11" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_11__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council notes that while some parts of Somalia remain unstable, relative stability continues to prevail in significant portions of the country. The Council welcomes the evolution of the community-based peace-building activities and calls for the acceleration of comprehensive peace-building activities. The Council requests the Secretary-General to continue putting in place, in a coherent manner, preparatory activities on the ground for a comprehensive post-conflict peace-building mission in Somalia once security conditions permit, as stipulated in the statement by the President of the Council of 28 March 2002 (S/PRST/2002/8), which should take into account combating poverty and strengthening public institutions.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_12" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_12__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council stresses that a comprehensive post-conflict peace-building programme with special emphasis on disarmament, demobilization, rehabilitation and reintegration will be an important contribution towards the restoration of peace and stability in Somalia. The Council welcomes the contribution of Ireland, Italy and Norway to the Trust Fund for Peace-building in Somalia and calls on other donors to do the same without delay.</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_13" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_13__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council commends the work done by the United Nations Country Team, the Red Cross and Red Crescent movements and non‑governmental organizations in support of peace and reconciliation in Somalia. The Council encourages the Secretary-General to continue to support actively the IGAD-sponsored Somalia National Reconciliation Process and to continue to implement and enhance ongoing humanitarian and peace-building activities on the ground. </p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eId="para_14" class="SingleTxt">
        <content eId="para_14__content">
          <p xml:space="preserve">	“The Security Council reiterates its commitment to assist the Somali parties and support the IGAD mediation in the implementation of the steps and conclusions for peace, as adopted throughout the Somalia National Reconciliation Process.”</p>
        </content>
      </paragraph>
    </mainBody>
  </statement>
</akomaNtoso>